Good morning. Today we're going to
早上好 今天我们
talk about augmenting data structures.
要讲的是扩充的数据结构
And this is a --
这是一个——
Normally, rather than designing data structures from scratch,
通常来讲 与其凭空设计一个新的数据结构
you tend to take existing data structures
你会更倾向于拿一个现成的数据结构
and build your functionality into them.
添加你需要的功能
And that is a process we call data-structure augmentation.
我们把这个过程称之为数据结构的扩充
And this also today marks sort of the start
也就是说 从今天起我们要开始
of the design phase of the class.
进入到设计的阶段
We spent a lot of time doing analysis up to this point.
到目前为止我们花了很多时间来分析
And now we're still going to learn some new analytical techniques.
我们也将学习到一些新的分析技术
But we're going to start turning our focus more toward
不过现在 我们要把更多注意力放在
how is it that you design efficient data structures,
如何设计高效的数据结构
efficient algorithms for various problems?
以及高效的算法来应对各种问题
So this is a good example of the design phase.
在设计阶段中 这是个很好的例子
It is a really good idea, at this point, if you have not done so,
如果现在你还没有看过课本上的附录B的话
to review the textbook Appendix B.
我强烈推荐你去看看
You should take that as additional reading
你可以把它当成附加阅读材料
to make sure that you are familiar,
确保你对它足够熟悉
because over the next few weeks we're going to
因为接下来几周里我们会
hit almost every topic in Appendix B.
用到附录B里的很多很多东西
It is going to be brought to bear
它与我们现在的主题
on the subjects that we're talking about.
息息相关
If you're going to go scramble to learn that
如果你们一边忙着学习新的知识点
while you're also trying to learn the material,
一边又想学习附录B里的东西
it will be more onerous than
那样还莫不如
if you just simply review the material now.
现在简单的回顾一下附录B
We're going to start with an illustration
我们首先来看一个
of the problem of dynamic order statistics.
一个动态有序统计的例子
We are familiar with finding things
我们对查找都比较熟悉
like the median or the kth order statistic or whatever.
诸如找一个序列的中间的数 或者是第k个数什么的
Now we want to do the same thing
现在我们也是做同样的事
but we want to do it with a dynamic set.
不过这次是在一个动态集合上
Rather than being given all the data upfront,
数据不再是一下子全部直接列出了
we're going to have a set.  And then at some point
而是以集合的形式出现  在某些情况下
somebody is going to be doing typically insert and delete.
也会有像插入和删除这样的经典操作
And at some point somebody is going to say OK,
而在另一些情况下 有人却想
select for me the ith largest guy or the ith smallest guy
把第i大的数或者第i小的数找出来
——in the dynamic set. Or, something like OS-Rank of x.
这次是动态集  又或者像查找x的序之类的
The rank of x in the sorted order of the set.
就是将集合排序后 返回x处在第几个位置上
So either I want to just say, for example,  if I gave n over 2,
比如给你n/2这个数
if I had n elements in the set and I said n over 2,
假设集合里有n个元素 我想求第n/2个
I am asking for the median.
我想求集合里的中位数
I could be asking for the mean.
我也可能求平均值
I could be asking for quartile.
也可能求四分位数
Here I take an element and say,
我现在取一个集合里的元素
OK, so where does that element fall
我想知道这个元素
among all of the other elements in the set?
处于集合中的哪个位置
And, in addition, these are dynamic sets
还有 我想要的是动态的集合
so I want to be able to do insert and delete,
所以我需要这个集合可以进行插入和删除的操作
I want to be able to add and remove elements.
我要给它添加和移除元素
The solution we are going to look at for this one,
如何解决这个问题呢？
the basic idea is to keep the sizes of subtrees
基本的思想是在红黑树的结点上
in the nodes of a red-black tree.
记录下该结点的子树的大小
Let me draw a picture as an example.
我来画个图说明一下
In this tree - I didn't draw the NILs for this.
这个树里——我没画那些空结点
I am going to keep two values. I am going to keep the key.
我在结点上记录两个值 我会记录键值
And so for the keys,
这些键值
what I will do is just use letters of the alphabet.
我用英文字母来表示
And this is a red-black tree.
这是一个红黑树
Just for practice, how can I label this tree
那么来练习一下 我如何把这个树
so it's a red-black tree?
按照红黑树的形式来标记？
I haven't shown the NILs.
我没画那些空结点
Remember the NILs are all black.
那些空结点都是黑色的
How can I label this, red and black?
我怎么用红黑来进行标记？
Make sure it is a red-black tree.
从而确保满足红黑树的条件
Not every tree can be labeled as a red-black tree, right?
不是所有树都能标记成红黑树的 对吧
This is good practice because
这个练习挺好的
this sort of thing shows up on quizzes.
我们可能会在小测试里考到
Make F red, good, and everything else black,
把F标记成红色 很好 然后其他都是黑色
that is certainly a solution.
这肯定是正确答案之一
Because then that basically brings the level of this guy up to here.
因为这实际上是把P、H的提升了一层
Actually, I had a more complicated one
其实我有一个更复杂的方案
because it seemed like more fun.
因为复杂的方案更有趣一些
What I did was I made this guy black
这个方案就是把这个结点标成黑色
and then these two guys red and black and red,
这两个是红色的 然后黑色 红色
black and red, black and black.
黑 红 黑 黑
But your solution is perfectly good as well.
当然你提出的方案也很好
So we don't have any two reds in a row on any path.
这样所有路径上都没有两个连续的红色结点
And all the black height from any particular point going down
而且从任一结点到其每个叶子的所有路径
we get the same number of blacks whichever way we go.
都包含相同数目的黑色结点
Good. The idea here now is that,
很好 现在我们要做的是
we're going to keep the subtree sizes,
在这些结点上记录子树的大小
these are the keys that are stored in our dynamic set,
这些键值储存在这个动态数组里
we're going to keep the subtree sizes in the red-black tree.
我们要把子树的大小也记录在这个红黑树里
For example, this guy has size one.
比如 它的子树大小是1
These guys have size one because they're leaves.
这些结点都是叶子 所以它们的子树大小都是1
And then we can just work up.
然后我们继续向上算
So this has size three,
这个值是3
this guy has size five, this guy has size three,
这个是5 这个是3
and this guy has five plus three plus one is nine.
这个是5+3+1=9
In general, we will have size of x is equal to size of left of x
总体上 我们有size[x] = size[left[x]]
plus the size of the right child of x plus one.
+ size[right[x]] + 1
That is how I compute it recursively.
这是用递归的方法来计算
A very simple formula for what the size is.
只用一个很简单的式子来计算子树大小
It turns out that for the code that we're going to
而在实际编写代码
want to write to implement these operations,
实现这些运算时
it is going to be convenient to be talking about the size of NIL.
空结点的大小是很容易算的
So what is the size of NIL?
那么空结点的大小是多少？
Zero. Size of NIL, there are no elements there.
就是0 意思是这里没有元素
However, in most program languages,
但在大多数编程语言中
if I take size of NIL, what will happen?
我对空值取值会发生什么？
You get an error. That is kind of inconvenient.
会报错 这就很不爽了
What I have to do in my code is that everywhere that size of NIL
在代码里 我需要取空结点大小
that I might want to take size of NIL, I have to say
意思是 我需要对空结点取大小
or take the size of anything,
或者对任意结点取大小
I have to say, well, if it's NIL then return zero,
我们可以这样实现 当结点是空结点时返回0
otherwise return the size field, etc.
否则返回子树的大小
There is an implementation trick
我们实现时可以用一个技巧
that we're going to use to simplify that.
来简化这个方法
It's called using a sentinel.
这个技巧叫标记法
A sentinel is nothing more than a dummy record.
所谓的标记其实就是一个伪记录
Instead of using a NIL, we will actually use a NIL sentinel.
我们用一个空标记来表示空的结点
We will use a dummy record for NIL
给空结点一个伪记录
such that size of NIL is equal to zero.
这样空结点的大小就等于0了
Instead of any place I would have used NIL in the tree,
这样 在这些原来是空结点的地方
instead I will have a special record that I will call NIL.
我都放一个特殊的空的记录
But it will be a whole record.
但这的确是一个完好的记录
And that way I can set its size field to be zero,
然后我就可以设置它的值为0
and then I don't have to check that as a special case.
这样我就不用考虑空结点的特殊情况了
That is a very common type of programming trick to use,
这是在编程中很常用的技巧
is to use sentinels to simplify code
就是用标记来简化代码
so you don't have all these boundary cases
这样你就不用考虑那些边界条件
or you don't have to write an extra function
也不用为特殊情况写额外的函数
when all I want to do is just index the size of something.
就能取到你想要的子树大小的值
Everybody with me on that?
大家都跟上了吧？
So let's write the code for OS-Select given this representation.
那根据这个 我们就可以写OS-Select的代码了
And this is going to basically give us
它的功能是返回
the ith smallest in the subtree rooted at x.
以x为根的子树中 第i小的元素
It's actually going to be a little bit more general.
这里我们会写得更加一般化
If I want to implement the OS-Select i of up there,
如果只是实现上面的OS-Select
I basically give it the root and i.
其实需要根结点和i
But we're going to build this recursively so it's going
但这里 我们用递归的方法来实现
to be helpful to have the node
这样有助于我们找到
in which we're trying to find the subtree.
子树里所求的那个结点
Here is the code.
这是代码
This is the code.
此乃代码也
And let's just see how it works
我们来看看它的原理
and then we will argue why it works.
然后来说明一下它的可行性
As an example, let's do OS-Select of the root and 5.
比如我们求OS-Select(root,5)
We're going to find the fifth largest in the set.
意思是求在整个集合里第5大的数
We have OS-Select of the root and 5. This is inconvenient.
直接可以写成OS-Select(root,5) 哇离得好远
We start out at the top,
我们从树的顶部开始找
well, let's just switch the boards. Here we go.
哦 我换一块黑板
We start at the top, and i is the root.
我们从顶端开始 i是根结点【译注：口误】
Excuse me, i is 5, sorry, and the root. i=5.
哦 对不起 是从根结点开始 然后i=5
We want to find the fifth largest.
我们要找到第5大的数
We first compute this value k. k is the size of left of x plus 1.
我们先来算k值 k = size[left[x]] + 1
What is that value? What is k anyway? What is it?
这是个什么值？k究竟是什么？
Well, in this case it is 6. Good. But what is the meaning of k?
嗯 这里它的值是6 不过k到底是神马意思？
[Student]Inaudible
学生：
[Professor]The order. The rank.
教授：就是当前结点的顺序 也就是秩
Good, the rank of the current node.
对 就是当前结点的秩
This is the rank of the current node.
这就是当前结点的秩
k is always the size of the left subtree plus 1.
k就是左侧子树的结点数+1
That is just the rank of the current node.
而这正好就是当前结点的秩
We look here and we say, well, the rank is k.
我们看到这里发现 哦 秩等于k
Now, if it is equal then we found the element we want.
如果i和k相等 那么这就是我们要找的那个元素
But, otherwise, if i is less,
如果i比k小
we know it's going to be in the left subtree.
我们就应该在左边的子树里面找
All we're doing then is recursing in the left subtree.
然后我们就在左子树里继续递归这个操作
And here we will recurse. We will want the fifth largest one.
于是我们递归到这边 我们要找第五大的元素
And now this time k is going to be equal to what?
这次k的值是多少？
Two. Now here we say, OK, this is bigger,
是2 这里我们发现i的值更大
so therefore the element we want
所以我们要找的那个元素
is going to be in the right subtree.
就应该藏在这边的右子树里
But we don't want the ith largest guy in the right subtree,
不过我们想要的并不是这个子树里第i大的
because we already know there are going to be two guys over here.
因为那边还有两个呢
We want the third largest guy in this subtree.
我们想求的其实是这个子树里第三大的元素
We have i equals 3 as we recurse into this subtree.
那么我们在这个子树进行递归的时候 i的值就为3
And now we compute k for here. This plus 1 is 2.
然后我们来计算这里的k值 这个值加上1 就是2
And that says we recursed right here.
i还是比k大 所以递归在右侧进行
And then we have i=1, k=1,
在这里i和k都等于1
and we return in this code a pointer to this node.
i和k都相等了 于是这里我们返回该结点的指针
So this returns a pointer to the node containing H whose key is H.
所以这个函数的返回值 就是关键字为H的结点的指针
Just to make a comment here,
这里加个注释
we discovered k is equal to the rank of x.
我们知道k等于x的秩
Any questions about what is going on in this code?
对于这个代码有什么疑问吗
OK. It's basically just finding its way down.
好的 其实我们是在不断地往下递归
The subtree sizes help it make the decision
用子树的大小来决定路径的方向
as to which way it should go to find which is the ith largest.
直到找到第i大的那个元素
We can do a quick analysis.
我们简单分析一下
On our red-black tree, how long does OS-Select take to run?
在我们的这个红黑树上 OS-Select的运行时间会是多少
Yeah? Yeah, order log n if there are n elements in the tree.
嗯？是的 对于有n个元素的树就是O(log n)
Because the red-black tree is a balance tree.
因为红黑树是平衡的
Its height is order log n.
它的高度是log n
In fact, this code will work on any tree
其实这个代码可以适用于任何
that has order log n the height of the tree.
高度为O(log n)的树
And so if you have a guaranteed height,
那么如果你能保证树的高度
the way that red-black trees do, you're in good shape.
就像红黑树这样的 那就好办多了
OS-Rank, we won't do but it is in the book,
OS-Rank 书上有这部分内容 不过我们就不细说了
also gets order log n. Here is a question I want to pose.
它的运行时间也是O(log n) 那好 现在我有一个问题
Why not just keep the ranks themselves? Yeah?
为什么不直接让这些结点记录自己的秩呢？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：...
[Professor]It's the node itself.
[教授]：就是结点自己
Otherwise, you cannot take left of it.
要不然你不能取到左子树
I mean, if we were doing this in a decent language,
其实如果我们用的是正规的编程语言的
strongly typed language there would be no confusion.
那么我们的代码就会足够规范 也就不会有歧义
But we're writing in this pseudocode that is good
不过我们用的只是伪代码 这样固然很好
because it's compact, which lets you focus on the algorithm.
因为这样很简洁 可以让我们更专注于算法
But, of course, it doesn't have
不过 当然啦
a lot of the things you would really want
伪代码肯定不会有
if you were programming things of scale
你真正编程时要考虑的东西
like type safety and so forth. Yeah?
诸如类型安全性这些 什么？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：...
[Professor]It is basically hard to maintain when you modify it.
教授：对 当你对树进行修改的时候 维护这个树将会很费劲
For example, if we actually kept the ranks in the nodes,
比如 我们在每个结点都保存它们自己的秩
certainly it would be easy to find the element of a given rank.
这样的确可以非常容易地找到 秩是给定值的元素
But all I have to do is insert the smallest element,
不过如果我想要插入一个最小的元素
an element that is smaller than all of the other elements.
比整个树里面的所有元素都要小
And what happens? All the ranks have to be changed.
那会怎么样？那样所有记录的秩都要修改
Order n changes have to be made if that's what I was maintaining,
这样的话维护就需要O(n)这样巨大的花费
whereas with subtree sizes that's a lot easier.
不过如果我记录的是子树大小 那事情就简单了
Because it's hard to maintain
因为如果红黑树被修改了
when the red-black tree is modified.
记录秩的话就会变得很难维护了
And that is the other sort of tricky thing
这也是需要注意的技巧
when you're augmenting a data structure.
如果要对数据结构进行扩充的话
You want to put in the things that your operations go fast,
你想加点东西让它运行得更快
but you cannot forget that there are already underlying operations
但别忘了 这个数据结构已有的一些基本运算
on the data structure that have to be maintained in some way.
你还要维护这些基本运算
Can we close this door, please?
那门帮着关一下呗
Thank you. We have to look at what are the modifying operations
谢了 我们不仅要关注如何构造树的修改操作
and how do we maintain them.
而且还要学会维护它们
The modifying operations for red-black trees
红黑树的修改操作有
are insert and delete.
插入和删除
If I were augmenting a binary heap,
如果我对二叉堆进行扩充
what operations would I have to worry about?
我该考虑哪些运算？
If I were augmenting a heap, what are the modifying operations?
如果对堆的扩张 哪些是堆的修改型运算？
Binary min heap, for example, classic priority queue?
比如对于二叉最小堆这样经典的优先队列
Who remembers heaps? What are the operations on a heap?
有谁还记得堆？堆上的运算有哪些？
There's a good final question.
哦 这个用来当期末考试题不错嘛
Take-home exam, don't worry about it.
课上留的作业你们都无所谓
Final, worry about it. What are the operations on a heap?
一提到期末考试就着急了 那么堆上的运算有哪些？
Just look it up on Books 24 or whatever it is, right?
可以看一看教科书嘛
AnswerMan? What does AnswerMan say?
大神？这位大神怎么说？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：...
[Professor]OK. And? If it's a min heap.
[教授]：好的 如果这是个最小堆
It's min, extract min, typical operations and insert.
查找最小值 取出最小值 最典型的操作 还有插入元素
And of those which are modifying? Insert and extract min, OK?
有哪些会对树进行修改？插入和取出最小值 对吧？
So, min is not. You don't have to worry about min
嗯 查找最小值没对树改动 不用担心
because all that is is a query.
因为它充其量只是在进行查询
You want to distinguish operations on a dynamic data structure
在动态数据结构上你会用到各种运算
those that modify and those that don't,
有些会对数据经行修改 有些不会
because the ones that don't modify the data structure
那些不修改数据的运算
are all perfectly fine as long
可以一直很好地运行
as you haven't destroyed information.
除非你把你的数据销毁了
The queries, those are easy.
查询总是很容易
But the operations that modify the data structure,
不过对于那些对数据结构进行修改的运算
those we're very concerned about in making sure we can maintain.
我们就要考虑他们的稳定性了
Our strategy for dealing with insert and delete in this case
这种情况下我们插入删除时采取的策略
is to update the subtree sizes
是随时更新子树的大小
---- when inserting or deleting.
与插入和删除同步进行
For example, let's look at what happens
我们来试试 比如说现在
when I insert k. Element key k.
我向树里面插入一个k 键值为K
I am going to want to insert it in here, right?
算法的过程是先把它插到这个地方
What is going to happen to this subtree size
子树大小有什么变化？
if I am inserting k in here?
如果我把k插到这的话？
This is going to increase to 10. And then I go left.
字数大小就变到10了 然后向左边走
This one is going to increase to 6.
这个就变成6
Here it is going to increase to 4. Here 2.
这边变成4 然后这里是2
And then I will put my k down there with a 1.
插入的k就放在这个地方 子树大小就是1
So I just updated on the way down. Pretty easy.
就是沿着这条路径一直更新下来 没什么难度
Yeah? But now it's not a red-black tree anymore.
嗯？ 对 现在已经不是一个红黑树了
You have to rebalance, so you must also handle rebalancing.
你需要重新使它平衡 使它回到平衡的状态
Because, remember, and this is something that people tend to forget
因为人们总是习惯性地忘记
so it's always, I think,
所以我总是认为
helpful when I see patterns going on
有必要和你们说一下
to tell everybody what the pattern is
程序应该怎么走
so that you can be sure of it in your work
这样当你们自己遇到这样的情况时
that you're not falling into that pattern.
不会犯这样的错误
What people tend to forget when they're doing red-black trees is
人们在红黑树上进行运算时 总是忘记平衡的事
they tend to remember the tree insert part of it,
普通树的插入当然很好做
but red-black insert,
不过红黑插入
that RB insert procedure actually has two parts to it.
红黑插入是包含了两个步骤的
First you call tree insert and then you have to rebalance.
不仅要进行树的插入 插入之后还有使树平衡
And so you've got to make sure you do
所以你要请确保
the whole of the red-black insert.
你做的是完整的红黑树插入
Not just the tree insert part. We just did the tree insert part.
而不仅仅是树插入的部分 我们已经完成了插入部分的工作
That was easy. We also have to handle rebalancing.
这很简单 不过我们还要使之平衡
So there are two types of things we have to worry about.
所以我们要关心两件事
One is red-black color changes.
首先是红黑颜色的改变
Well, unfortunately those have no effect on subtree sizes.
不过他们对子树的大小没有影响
If I change the colors of things, no effect, no problem.
如果我只是改变颜色 那这不会对子树大小有任何影响
But also the interesting one is rotations.
不过我们还有一个很有意思的东西 旋转
Rotations, it turns out, are fairly easy to fix up.
我们会发现旋转造成的影响很容易修正
Because when I do a rotation,
因为当我做旋转的时候
I can update the nodes based on the children.I will show you that.
我可以从子结点来进行更新 等会我给你们看
You basically look at children and fix up,
只是根据子结点来进行修复
in this case, in order one time per rotation.
这种情况下 每次旋转的花费是O(1)
For example, imagine that
比如想象一下
I had a piece of my tree that looked like this.
有一个树的某部分是像这个样子的
And let's say it was 7, 3, 4, the subtree sizes.
这些结点的子树大小分别是7 3 4
I'm not going to put the values in here.
这里我就不给定键值了
And I did a right rotation on that edge
然后我在这条边上做右旋转
to put them the other way.
把他们调过来
And so these guys get hooked up this way.
于是他们就这样连在一起了
Always the three children stay as three children.
子结点还是三个
We just swing this guy over to there
于是我们把结点换上去
and make this guy be the parent of the other one.
然后让另外这个结点为剩下的父结点
And so now the point is that
那么现在关键就是
I can just simply update this guy to be,
把这些值更新一下
well, he's got 8, 3 plus 4 plus 1
这是8 3+4+1=8
using our formula for what the size is.
用这个子树大小的公式来算
And now, for this one, it's going to be 8 plus 7 plus 1 is 16,
另外这个数就是8+7+1=16
or, if I think about it,
或者可以这么想
it's going to be whatever that was before
无论下面的子树是什么样的
because I haven't changed this subtree size with a rotation.
旋转这个运算都不会改变它的子树大小
Everything beneath this edge is still beneath this edge.
这下面的所有东西都还在下面
And so I fixed it up in order one time.
所以这里我们用O(1)的时间就解决了
There are certain other types of operations
当然这里肯定还有很多其他不同的运算
sometimes that occur where this isn't the value.
放在这里的可能是不一样的值
If I wasn't doing subtree sizes
我记录的可能不是子树大小
but was doing some other property of the subtree,
而是子树的其他性质
it could be that this was no longer 16
有可能这个值不是16了
in which case the effect might propagate up towards the root.
而这个性质也会一直传递到根结点
There is a nice little lemma in the book
书里有一个不错的小引理
that shows the conditions under which you can make sure that
说的就是你可以保证重新平衡这个过程
the re-balancing doesn't cost you too much.
并不会有太高的花费
So that was pretty good.
这就很不错
Now, insert and delete, that is all we have to do for rotations,
那么现在插入和删除 对于旋转我们要做的就这么多
are therefore still order log n time,
花费时间是O(log n)
because a red-black tree only has to do order one rotations.
因为红黑树的旋转只花费O(1)
Do they normally take constant time?
普通来说 他们花费也是常数阶吗？
Well, they still take constant time.
是的 他们的花费都是常数阶
They just take a little bit bigger constant.
只不过是大一点的常数阶
And so now we've been able to build this great data structure
现在我们就可以完成这个给力的数据结构了
that supports dynamic order statistic queries
它支持动态有序查询
and it works in order log n time
它的工作时间都是O(log n)
for insert, delete and the various queries.
对于插入 删除 还有各种各样的查询而言
OS-Select. I can also just search for an element.
无论是OS-Select 又或者是查找一个元素
I have taken the basic data structure
我们从一个基础的数据结构出发
and have added some new operations on it.
并且添加了许多新的运算
Any questions about what we did here?
这部分有什么问题吗
Do people understand this reasonably well?
大家都对这部分融会贯通了？
OK. Then let's generalize, always a dangerous thing.
好的 那我们来总结一下吧 做总结如履薄冰啊
Augmenting data structures.
那么关于扩展的数据结构
What I would like to do is give you a little methodology
我想告诉你们一套小小的步骤
for how you go about doing this safely
能够让你们不会犯错
so you don't forget things.
也不会忘掉重要的步骤
The most common thing, by the way,
通常来说 啊 对了
if there is an augmentation problem on the take-home
如果你们在作业里遇到关于扩张的问题
or if there is one on the final,
或者在期末考试里遇到
I guarantee that probably a quarter of the class
我保证大约四分之一的人
will forget the rotations if they augmented red-black tree.
在对红黑树进行扩张时 会忘记旋转这个步骤
I guarantee it. Anyway,
妥妥的 总而言之
here is a little methodology to check yourself.
有个方法可以用来进行检查
As I mentioned, the reason why this is so important is
就像我说过的 之所以它如此重要
because this is, in practice,
是因为在实际应用中
the thing that you do most of the time.
大部分的时间你都会用到扩张
You don't just use a data structure as given.
通常我们不会用现成的数据结构
You take a data structure.
当你拿到一个数据结构
You say I have my own operations I want to layer onto this.
你会想要添加自己的一些运算
We're going to give a methodology.
我们来讲这个步骤
And what I will do, as I go along,
接着我刚才说的
is will use the example of order statistics trees
我们会以一个有序统计树为例
to illustrate the methodology.
来说明这个步骤
It is four steps.
分为四步
The first is choose an underlying data structure.
首先选择一个基础的数据结构
Which in the case of order statistics tree was what?
这里 我们选择了什么有序统计树？
Red-black tree. And the second thing we do is we figure out
红黑树 第二步是我们要如何
what additional information we wish
在这样的数据结构中
to maintain in that data structure.
维护一些附加的信息
Which in this case is the subtree sizes.
在这种情况下就是子树的大小
Subtree sizes is what we keep for this one.
我们保存的信息就是子树的大小
And when we did this we could make mistakes, right?
这里很容易出错哦亲~
We could have said, oh, let's keep the rank.
我们可能会想 哦 直接记录秩就好了
And we start playing with it and discover we can do that.
于是我们就这么做 其实也行得通
It just goes really slowly.
只不过速度实在不敢恭维
It takes some creativity to figure out what is the information
我们需要一些想象力来想出
that you're going to be able to keep,
有哪些信息是我们能够保留
but also to maintain the other properties that you want.
同时又能维持所需的其他性质不变
The third step is verify that the information can be maintained
第三步就是验证这个数据结构上的信息
---- for the modifying operations on the data structure.
不会受修改操作的影响
And so in this case, for OS trees,
这种情况下 对于OS树
the modifying operations were insert and delete.
它的修改操作就是插入和删除
And, of course, we had to make sure we dealt with rotations.
当然 我们还要处理旋转的问题
And because rotations are part of that we could break it down
因为旋转是其中的一步 所以我们可以把它们分解成
into the tree insert, the tree delete and rotations.
树插入+旋转、树删除+旋转
And once we've did that everything was fine.
只要这个搞定了 其他都好办了
We didn't, for this particular problem,
不过对于这个特殊的问题
have to worry about color changes. But that's another thing
我们要关心颜色的变化 不过那就是
that under some things you might have to worry about.
之后你们才会关注的东西了
For some reason the color made a difference.
不知道怎么回事颜色变得重要了
Usually that doesn't make a difference.
通常颜色并不是很重要的
And then the fourth step is to develop new operations.
第四步就是建立新的运算
Presumably that use the info that you have now stored.
假设新的数据已经存好了 然后开始使用这些信息
And this was OS-Select and OS-Rank,
这个是OS-Select和OS-Rank
which we didn't give but which is there.
虽然我们这里没有讲OS-Rank
And also it's a nice little puzzle to figure out yourself,
但这个问题很有意思 你们可以自己考虑下
how you would build OS-Rank. Not a hard piece of code.
如何建立OS-Rank这个函数 并不是很难
This methodology is not actually the way you do this.
这套方法实际上不是按部就班的
This is one of these things that's more like a checklist,
这更像是一个检查清单
because you see whether or not you've got --
给你检查都完成了哪些
When you're actually doing this
在实际应用中
maybe you developed the new operations first.
可能你会先写一个新的运算函数
You've got to keep in mind the new operations
你先记下这个新的运算
while you're verifying that the information
然后验证什么样的信息
you're storing can be here.
可以储存在这里
Maybe you will then go back
也许你回过头来
and change this and sort of sort through it.
换个顺序把这些步骤再来一遍
This is more a checklist that when you're done
这就是一个完成时的检查列表
this is how you write it up.
你可以像这样写
This is how you document that what you've done is,
就像这样 把你做了什么用文档记录下来
in fact, a good thing. You have a checklist.
这样很不错哦 你就有一个检查列表了
Here is my underlying data structure.
这就是我的基础的数据结构
Here is the addition information I need.
这边有些附加的新的信息
See, I can still support the modifying operations
看吧 我仍然保持了数据结构中
that the data structure used to have
原有的运算
and now here are my new operations and see what those are.
同时这里我还添加了我自己的新运算
It's really a checklist.
这的确是一个检查列表
Not a prescription for the order in which you do things.
不是让你一步不差地按照这个顺序来做
You must do all these steps, not necessarily in this order.
这些步骤都是必须的 但不一定是按这个顺序来的
This is a guide for your documentation.
这是一套成文的设计指引
When we ask for you to augment a data structure,
当你要扩张一个数据结构的时候
generally we're asking you to tell us what the four steps are.
总的来说 就是让你说清楚这四步都是什么
It will help you organize your things.
这对你进行管理很有帮助
It will also help make sure
而且也可以确保你
you don't forget some step along the way.
在做的过程中不会忘了什么
I've seen people who have added the information
我见过有人进行信息的添加
and developed new operations
以及建立新的运算
but completely forgot to verify that
不过它们完全忘记了
the information could be maintained.
验证要保留的信息
So you want to make sure that you've done all those.
所以你要确保这些都完成了
Usually you have to play -- -- with interactions
你要对这种每一步之间的相互作用
——between steps.
有所了解
It's not just a do this, do this, do this.
并不是做完了这个 再做那个 那么简单
We're going to do now a more complicated data structure.
现在我们来做一个更复杂的数据结构
It's not that much more complicated,
并不复杂多少
but its correctness is actually kind of challenging.
不过要正确地实现它却是个挑战
And it is actually a very practical and useful data structure.
其实 这个数据结构相当实用
I am amazed at how many people aren't aware that
但我对 有很多人都没有意识到 感到很惊讶
there are data structures of this nature that are useful for them
本来这种数据结构对他们很有帮助
when I see people writing really slow code.
但他们却用很低效的代码
And so the example we're going to do is interval trees.
我们要讲的这个例子就是区间树
And the idea of this is that
区间树的思想就是
we want to maintain a set of intervals.
要保存一系列的区间
For example, time intervals.
比如说时间区间
I have a whole database of time intervals
我有整整一个数据库的时间区间
that I'm trying to maintain.
我都想维护
Let's just do an example here.
我们来看一个例子
This is going from 7 to 10, 5 to 11 and 4 to 8,
这些区间分别是7到10 5到11 4到8
from 15 to 18, 17 to 19 and 21 to 23.
15到18 17到19 21到23
This is a set of intervals.
这是一系列区间
And if we have an interval i,
如果我们有一个区间i
let's say this is interval i, which is 7,10.
我们就设这个从7到10的区间为i
We're going to call this endpoint the low endpoint of i
我们把这个端点成为i的低端点
and this we're going to call the high endpoint of i.
这个则是i的高端点
The reason I use low and high rather than left or right is
之所以用的是高低而不是左右
because we're going to have a tree,
是因为我们使用的是一棵树
and we're going to want the left subtree and the right subtree.
以免跟树的左子树和右子树混淆
So if I start saying left and right for intervals and left and right
所以如果我用左右来表示区间和树
for tree we're going to get really confused.
这个东西就说不清楚了
This is also a tip.  Let me say when you're coding,
这也是个提醒 当你在编程的时候
you really have to think hard sometimes about the words
切记要仔细考虑你的命名
that you're using for things,
尤其是对于你自己使用的东西
especially things like left and right
特别是像左右这种命名
because they get so overused throughout programming.
因为他们在编程中已经被用烂了
It's a good idea to come up with a whole wealth of synonyms
有一个好办法是使用各种同义词
for different situations so that it is clear in any piece of code
以应对不同的情况 从而保证代码的整洁
when you're talking, for example,
比如说吧
about the intervals versus the tree,
当区间遇上了树
because we're going to have both going on here.
这里我们要同时使用他们两个
And what we're going to do is
我们要做的就是
we want to support insertion and deletion of intervals here.
我们想要能够插入和删除区间
And we're going to have a query,
而且我们将会用到查询
which is going to be the new operation we're going to develop,
这是我们要建立的新操作
which is going to be to find an interval, any interval
它是要查询集合里所有的区间
in the set that overlaps a given query interval.
与给定区间发生重合的有哪些
So I give you a query interval like say 6, 14
比如给定一个区间 [6,14]
and you can return this guy or this guy,
你就可以返回这个区间 这个
this guy, couldn't return any of these
还有这个 剩下这些就不行了
because these are all less than 14.
因为他们都小于14
So I can return any one of those.
所以这几个都可以是返回值
I only have to return one.
我只要返回一个就好了
I just have to find one guy that overlaps.
只要返回一个有重叠的就行
Any question about what we're going to be setting up here?
对于我们要做的东西都清楚了吧？
OK. Our methodology is we're going to pick,
好的 这就用到了我们的方法论
first of all, step one.
首先 第一步
And here is our methodology.
嗯 我们的方法论在这
Step one is we're going chose underlying data structure.
第一步是我们要选择基础的数据结构
Does anybody have a suggestion as to what data structure
有哪位能给个建议不？
we ought to use here to support interval trees?
我们用什么来实现区间树？
What data structure should we try to start here
我们用什么样的数据结构
to support interval trees?
能够支持这样的区间树？
Anybody have any idea?
摆脱谁去终结了这个问题吧？
A red-black tree. A binary search tree. Red-black tree.
红黑树 二叉搜索树 红黑树
We're going to use a red-black tree.
好吧 我们要用的是红黑树
Oh, I've got to say what it is keyed on.
我要讲一下关于关键字
What is going to be the key for my red-black tree?
我用什么来作这个红黑树的关键字？
For each interval, what should I use for a key?
对于每个区间 我用什么作为关键字？
This is where there are a bunch of options, right?
有很多种选择是吧？
Throw out some ideas.
告诉我你们的奇思妙想吧
It's always better to branch than it is to prune.
开发新分支总比剪枝好
You can always prune later,
你可以过后再剪枝
but if you don't branch you will never get the chance to prune.
但如果你不开发新的分支 你就永远没有剪枝的机会
So generation of ideas.
所以爆发你们的小宇宙吧
You'll need that when you're doing the design phase
在设计阶段 你会需要这样做
and doing the take-home exam. Yeah?
在家做作业也要用到 是吧？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：...
[Professor]We're calling that the low endpoint.
[教授]：我们把这个称为低端点
OK, you could do low endpoint.
好吧 你可以用低端点来做
What other ideas are there?
还有什么别的想法吗
High end point. Now you can look at low endpoint, high endpoint.
高端点 嗯 你们很关注低端点和高端点
Well, between low and high which is better?
好吧 这两个端点之间哪个更好？
That one is not going to matter, right?
好像都没所谓 对吧？
So doing high versus low, we don't have to consider that,
所以高对低 我们可以先不考虑这个
but there is another natural point you want to think about
不过你们可能也会想到 还有一个很常用的点
using like the median, the middle point.
比如说中点 中间点
At least that is symmetric. What do you think?
至少是对称的 你们认为呢？
What else might I use? The length?
我还会用到什么？长度？
I think the length doesn't feel to me productive.
我感觉长度不是很靠谱
This is just purely a matter of intuition.
只是单纯地凭直觉判断的
It doesn't feel productive,
感觉上不是很给力
because if I know the length I don't know
因为就算我知道长度了
where it is so it's going to be hard to
我也很难弄清楚它到底在哪
maintain information about where it is for queries.
而且查询时很难追踪它的位置信息
It turns out we're going to use the low left endpoint,
所以我们要用的是低端点
but I think to me that was sort of a surprise
不过我有些许惊讶
that you'd want to use that and not the middle one.
你们居然没有人想用中点来做
Because you're favoring one endpoint over the other.
因为你们都喜欢这个端点
It turns out that's the right thing to do, surprisingly.
但其实这么做挺好的 很神奇嘛
There is another strategy.
还有一种策略
Actually, there's another type of tree called a segment tree.
还有另外一种树 叫做线段树
Actually, what you do is
实际上 你要做的就是
you store both the left and right endpoints separately in the tree.
把左右两个端点分别存放在树里
And then you maintain a data structure
然后你要维护这个数据结构
where the line segments go up through the tree on to the other.
使线段能够通过树相连
There are lots of things you can do,
你可以有很多种选择
but we're just going to keep it keyed on the low endpoint.
不过我们这里就用低端点作为关键字好了
That's why this is a more clever data structure in some ways.
这也是为什么这个数据结构更智能一些
Now, this is harder. That is why this is a clever data structure.
好的 这里是难点了 这个数据结构真的很智能
What are we going to store in the
我们要在这里储存的是
I think any of those ideas are good ideas
我感觉这里的方法都不错
to throw out and look at.
都能登大雅之堂
You don't know which one is going to work until you play with it.
但直到真正用到它之前 你永远也不知道哪个更好
This one, though, is, I think, much harder to guess.
这个 我感觉更难以猜到
You're going to store in a node
你要在一个结点里储存...
the largest value, I will call it m, in the subtree rooted at that node.
这个结点的子树的最大值m
We'll draw it like this, a node like this.
这样画一下 一个这样的结点
We will put the interval here and we will put the m value here.
我们把区间值放在上面 m值放在下面
Let's draw a picture.
画幅图说明一下
Once again, I am not drawing the NILs.
再说一次 空的叶子结点我就不画了
I hope that that is a search tree
我希望这是一个查找树
that is keyed on the low left endpoint. 4, 5, 7, 15, 17, 21.
关键字就是这些低端点 4, 5, 7, 15, 17, 21
It is keyed on the low left endpoint.
以低端点为关键字
If this a red-black tree, let's just do another practice.
不过因为这是一个红黑树 所以我们还需要先做一件事
How can I color this so that it is a legal red-black tree?
我如何对它上色 使之成为一个合法的红黑树？
Not too relevant to what we're doing right now
虽然跟我们所做的没什么太大联系
But a little drill doesn't hurt sometimes.
不过有时候拿来试着练习一下也不错
Remember, the NILs are not there and they are all black.
记住 空结点不会显示出来而且它们都是黑的
And the root is black. I will give that one to you.
还有根结点也是黑的 这个我给你们画出来
Good. This will work. You sort of go through a little puzzle.
很好 估计能行 你们通过了一个考验
A logic puzzle.
一个逻辑上的考验
Because this is really short
因为这条边实在是很短
so it better not have any reds in it.
所以最好不要有红色在里面
This has got to be black.
这个是黑的
Now, if I'm going to balance the height,
现在我想要平衡高度
I have got to have a layer of black here.
我需要这里有一层结点都是黑的
It couldn't be that one. It's got to be these two.
不能是这个 应该是这两个
Good. Now let's compute the m value for each of these.
不错 现在我们来对这些结点分别计算m值
It's the largest value in the subtree rooted at that node.
m是以该结点为根的子树中的最大值
What's the largest value in the subtree rooted at this node? 10.
这个结点下的子树最大值是多少？10
And in this one? 18. In this one? 8. 18.
这个呢？18 这个？8 18
That one is 23 and that is 23.
这个是23 这个也是23
In general, m is going to be
总而言之 m就是
the maximum of three possible values.
三个可能值里面的最大的
Either the high point of the interval at x
或者是x的高端值
or m of the left of x or m of the right of x.
或者是x左子结点的m值 或者是x右子结点的m值
Does everybody see that?
都懂了吗？
It is going to be m of x for any node.
这三种都可能是任意结点x的m值
I just have to look, what is the maximum here,
我只需要看一下这里的最大值是多少
what is the maximum here
这里的又是多少
and what is the high point of the interval.
还有区间的高端点是多少
Whichever one of those is largest,
这三个值的最大值
that's the largest for that subtree.
同时也是子树里面的最大值
The modifying operations.
那么关于修改操作
Let's first do insert. How can I do insert?
我们先来做插入 插入怎么做？
There are two parts.
分为两部分
The first part is to do the tree insert,
第一部分就是树插入
just a normal insert into a binary search tree.
就是普通二叉搜索树的插入
What do I do? Insert a new interval?
我怎么做？怎么插入新的区间？
Insert a new interval here?
在这里插入一个新的区间？
How can I fix up the m's?
我怎么搞定这些m呢？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：...
[Professor]That's right. You just go down the tree
[教授]：没错 你只要沿着树走
and look at my current interval.
看一看当前的结点
And if it's got a bigger max,
如果出现了更大的最大值
this is something that is going into that subtree.
因为这可是要插入到树里的
If its high endpoint is bigger than the current max,
如果新的高端点比现有的最大值还要大的话
update the current max.
那就更新结点
I just do that as I'm going through the insertion,
整个插入过程 我就做这个
wherever it happens to land up in every subtree that it hits,
无论经过哪棵子树
every node that it hits on the way down.
哪个结点 我都这么做
I just update it with the maximum wherever it happens to fall.
我只是在新的最大值所经过的路径上 不断地更新结点
Good. You just fix them on the way down.
很好 你就这样沿着这条路一直这么做下来
But we also have to do the other section.
不过我们还要做其他的部分
Also need to handle rotations.
还要做旋转的部分
So let's just see how we might do rotations as an example.
那么我们举个例子来看一下旋转的过程
Let's say this is 11, 15, 30.
我们设这个分别是 11,15,30
Let's say I'm doing a right rotation.
假设我们来做一个有旋转
This is coming off from somewhere.
这上面还有东西 就不画了
That is coming off.
上面省略
This is still going to be the child that has 30,
这些子结点还是30
the one that 14 and the one that has 19.
14和19
And so now we've rotated this way,
我们朝这边旋转
so this is the 11, 15 and this is the 6, 20.
于是这个是[11,15] 这边的是[6,20]
For this one, I just use my formula here.
我可以使用这个公式来解决
I just look here and say which is the biggest, 14, 15 or 19?
看看这里哪个是最大就行了 14,15还是19？
19. And I look here. Which is the biggest? 30, 19 or 20? 30.
是19  然后再看这里 那个数是最大的？嗯 30
Or, once again, it turns out, not too hard to show,
或者 嗯 再来一遍 这个也不是太难表示
that it's always whatever was there,
这里总会是这个数
because we're talking about the biggest thing in the subtree.
因为我们要的就是子树里面的最大值
And the membership of the subtree
而子树的所有成员
hasn't changed when we do the rotation.
并没有在旋转时发生改变
That just took me order one time to fix up.
这只用O(1)就能完成
Fixing up the m's during rotation takes O(1) time.
计算m值只需要O(1)的时间
So the total insert time is O(log n).
所以插入操作的总时间就是O(log n)
Once I figured out that this is the right information,
如果我明白这就是我要求的东西
of course we don't know what we're using this information for yet.
当然我们现在还不知道 这个有什么用
But once I know that that is the information,
不过一旦我知道了这就是我想要的
showing you that it works in certain delete continuing work
那么就能很容易得出 像删除这样的操作
in order log n time is easy.
都能在O(log n)时间内解决
Now, delete is actually a little bit trickier
删除其实是挺有技巧的
but I will just say it is similar.
不过我感觉也差不多
Because in delete you go through and you find something,
因为删除就是先进行遍历查找
you may have to go through the whole business of swapping it.
再进行一系列交换操作
If it's an internal node you've got to swap it
对于内部结点 我们要拿它
with its successor or predecessor.
和它的子代或父代交换
And so there are a bunch of things that have to be dealt with,
我们还有很多要处理的东西
but it is all stuff where
不过基本上就是
you can update the information using this thing.
如何用这些东西来更新
And it's all essentially local changes
本质上来说这些都是在更新过程中
when you're updating this information
在局部发生的变化
because you can do it essentially only on a path up from the root
因为你只是从根结点开始沿着一条路径走
and most of the tree is never dealt with.
对树的其他大部分都没有触碰到
I will leave that for you folks to work out.
这个就留给你们自己想吧
It's also in the book if you want to cheat,
友情提示一下 想偷懒的话就去看看书里的内容吧
but it is a good exercise.
不过用来练习还是不错的
Any questions about the first three steps?
前三步有什么问题吗？
Fourth step is new operations.
第四步就是新的运算了
Interval search of i is going to find an interval
对i的区间查找就是找到一个
that overlaps the interval i.
与区间i重叠的区间
So i here is an interval. It's got two coordinates.
i是一个区间  它有两个坐标
And this, rather than writing recursively,
还有 相比于用递归来写
we're going to write as, it's sort of going to be recursive,
虽然可以写成递归
but we're going to write it with a while loop.
不过我们会用一个while循环来写
You could write it recursively.
你可以用递归来写
The other one that we wrote, we could have written
而我要写的这一个函数
as a while loop as well and not had the recursive call.
会写成循环的形式 而不包含任何递归调用
Here we're going to basically just start x gets the root.
我们现在开始 把根结点的值赋给x
And then while --
然后呢
That is the code. Let's just see how it works.
这就是代码了 我们来看看它的工作原理
Let's search for the interval 14, 16 in this tree.
我们来搜索区间[14,16]
Let's see. x starts out at the root.
看看啊 x从根结点开始
And while it is not NIL,
当它不为空的时候
and it's not NIL because it's the root, what is this doing?
根结点显然不是空的 诶 我们现在在干什么呢？
Somebody tell me what that code does.
哪位能告诉我这代码是在干嘛？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：....
[Professor]Well, what is this doing?
[教授]：嗯 我们在做什么事情呢？
This is testing something between i and int of x.
这是对i和区间x做检测
Int of x is the interval stored at x.
区间x就是储存在x结点的区间
What is this testing for?
这个检测是在干嘛？
I hope I got it right.
我希望我弄对了
What is this testing for? Yeah?
这个检测在干嘛？嗯？
[Student]Inaudible
[学生]：...
[Professor]Above or below? I need just simple words.
[教授]：高了还是低了？你简单回答就好
Test for overlaps. In particular test whether they do or don't?
检测重叠的部分 具体一点的话   有没有重叠？
Do? Don't? If I get to this point,
有没有重叠？ 如果我到了这一点
what do I know about i and int of x?
关于i和区间x我都知道什么了？
Don't overlap. They don't overlap
没重叠 他们不重叠
because the high of one is smaller than the low of the other.
因为这个高端点小于这个低端点
The high of one is smaller than the low of the other.
高端点小于低端点
They don't overlap that way.
这么看来它们没重叠
Could they overlap the other way?
他们能以其他方式重叠吗？
No because we're testing also whether the low of the one
不会的 因为我们还检测了低端点
is bigger than the high of the other.
是否高于另一个的高端点
They're saying it's either like this or like this.
它们的关系是非此即彼
This is testing not overlap. That makes it simpler.
这样就检测出是不是重叠的 这把过程简化了
When I'm searching for 14, 16, I check here.
当我搜索[14,16]时 我检查这里
And I say do they overlap?
我看看他们重叠吗？
And the answer is, now we can understand it
答案就是 现在我们已经理解了
without having to go through all the arithmetic calculations,
不用经过完整的数学计算
no they don't overlap. If they did overlap, I found what I want.
他们不是重叠的 如果他们重叠 我就找到我想要的了
And what's going to happen?
然后该怎么做？
I am going to drop out of the while loop and just return x,
然后我就直接跳出循环 并返回x
because I will return something that overlaps.
因为我就是想返回那些重叠的东西
That is my goal. Here it says they don't overlap.
这就是我的目的 这里我们可以看出他们并不重叠
So then I say, well, if left of x is not NIL,
于是我就想啊 如果x的左结点不是空的
in other words, I've got a left child and low of i
换而言之 我已经有一个左子结点了 而且i的低端点
is less than or equal to m of left of x, then we go left.
小于等于x的左子的m值 于是我们从左边走
What happens in this case if I'm searching for 14, 16?
我如果搜索[14,16]会有什么结果？
Is the low of i less than or equal to m of left of x?
i的低端点是小于等于x左子的m值吗？
Low of i is 14.
i的下限为14
And I am searching. And is it less than 18?
我们来做一下搜索 这个是不是比18小？
Yes. Therefore, what do I do?
是的 那么我怎么做？
I go left and make x point to this guy.
我向左走然后让x指向它
Now I check. Does it overlap?
现在来检查一下 它重叠了吗？
No. I take a look at the left guy. It is 8.
没重叠 我看一下左边这个 是8
I compare 8 with 14, right? And is it lower?
8和14相比 对吧？是不是它更小？
No, so I go right.
不是 所以我向右走
And now I discover that I have an overlap here and it overlaps.
我在这里发现了一个重叠的部分 那么就是这货了
It returns then the 15, 18 as an overlapping one.
于是返回[15,18]作为一个重叠的区间
If I were searching for 12, 14.
如果我搜索[12,14]这个区间
I would go up to the top.
我从最上面开始
And I look, 12, 14, it doesn't overlap here.
于是我们来看 [12,14] 这里没有重叠
I look at the 18 and it is greater so I go left.
然后看见这个18了 于是我往左走
I then look here. Does it overlap?
到这里了 重叠了吗？
No. So then what happens?
没有 那么接下来怎么办？
I look at the left. It says I go right. I look here.
看一下左边 看来我应该往右边走 到这里
Then I go and I look at the left. It says, no, go right.
然后继续看左边 嗯 不行 还是要到右边
I go here, which is NIL, and now it is NIL. I return NIL.
到了这里 是个结点 于是我返回空值
And does 12, 14 overlap anything in the set?
[12,14]和集合里的其他区间有重叠的吗？
No. So, therefore, it always works.
没有 那看来这样的方法还是挺管用的
OK? OK. We're going to do correctness in a minute,
没问题吧？嗯 验算过程很快就能做完
but let's just do our analysis first so we don't have to do it
不过我们先来做一下分析 验算神马的先不做了
because the correctness is going to be a little bit tricky.
因为算起来其实是挺麻烦的
Time = O(lg n) because all I am doing is going down the tree.
时间是O(log n) 因为我做的就是沿着树从上到下走
It takes time proportional to the height of the tree.
花费的时间与树的高度是成正比的
That's pretty easy. If I need to list all overlaps,
很容易理解 如果我想要列出所有的重叠区间
suppose I want to list all the overlaps,
如果我想要列出所有重叠区间
how quickly can I do that?
我需要花费多长时间？
Can somebody suggest how I could use this
有没有谁给个建议 让我写出一个
as a subroutine to list all overlaps?
列出所有重叠部分的子程序？
Suppose I have k overlaps,
假设我有k个重叠区间
k intervals that overlap my query interval
k个与我要查询的区间重合的区间
and I want to find every single one of them,
我想找到他们中的每一个
how fast can I do that? How do I do it?
最快能有多快？我该怎么做？
How do I do it? If I search a second time,
怎么做？如果我只是再次搜索
I might get the same value.
那我得到的还是那个值
Yeah, there you go. Do what?
好的 请说 怎么做？
When you find it delete it. Put it over to the side.
找到了一个就删除一个 先把找到的拿出来
Find the next one, delete it until there are none left.
再找到下一个 然后删除 直到没有剩下的为止
And then, if I don't want to modify the data structure,
如果你不想修改数据结构
insert them all back in.
那就把他们再重新插入回去
It costs me k lg n if they are k overlaps.
对k个重叠区间花费就是O(k log n)
That's actually called an output sensitive algorithm.
这个就是我们所说的输出敏感算法
Because the running time of it depends upon
因为运行时间取决于
how much it outputs, so this is output sensitive.
它的输出数量 所以叫它输出敏感
The best to date for this problem, by the way,
这个问题的最好结果
wasting all is O(k+lg n) with a different data structure.
用另一种数据结构下花费是O(k + log n)
And, actually, that was open for a while as an open problem.
这是个开放性的问题
OK. Correctness. Why does this algorithm always work correctly?
好的 正确性 我们怎么知道算法总能正常工作？
The key issue of the correctness is that
正确性的关键就是
I am picking one way to go, left or right.
选择正确的方向 左或者右
And that's great, as long as it is in that subtree.
只要我选择了正确的子树就行
But how do I know that when I pick I decide I'm going to
比如说我选择了向左边走
go left that it might not be in the right subtree
我怎么能确定所要查找的区间
and I went the wrong way?
就是在左边呢？
Or, if I went right,
或者反过来
that I accidentally left one out on the left side?
如果我选了右边  又怎么确定左面没有所求的区间呢？
We're always going just one direction.
每次只能有一个选择
And that's sort of the cleverness of the code.
这就是代码里很巧妙的地方了
The theorem is let's let L be
有一个定理是说
the set of intervals i prime in the left of a node x.
如果L为x结点左子树里的i'区间的集合
And R be the set of i primes in the right of x.
R是右子树i'区间的集合
And now there are two parts I am going to show.
关键有两点
If the search goes right then the set of i prime in L,
如果搜索向右进行 那么L集合
such that i prime overlaps i is the empty set.
里的所有与i区间重合的i'区间为空集
That's the first thing I do.
这是第一点
If it goes right then there is nothing
也就是说如果搜索方向向右进行
in the left subtree that overlaps.
那么左子树里就一个重叠的区间都没有
It's always, whenever the code goes right, no problem,
这个定理恒成立 只要代码在算的时候往右走了
because there was nothing in the left subtree to be found.
因为左边的子树里 肯定没有重叠的区间
Does everybody understand what that says?
都明白这个讲的是啥了吧
We are going to prove this,
我们会证明的
but I want to make sure people understand.
不过我想让你们先理解一下
Because the second one is going to be harder to understand
因为第二点不太好理解
so you've got to make sure you understand this one first.
所以先把第一点弄明白吧
Any questions about this? OK. If the search goes left
有什么问题没？好的 如果搜索向左
——then the set of i prime in L such that i prime overlaps i,
而且发现L集合中i'和i的重叠区间是空集
empty set, implies that i prime
那么这说明——
——OK. What is this saying? If the search goes left,
好的 这里说了什么？ 如果往左搜索
if the left was empty,
如果左边是空集
in other words, if you went left and you discovered that
换而言之 如果你向左搜索
there was nothing in there to find,
不过一个符合条件的区间都没找到
no overlapping interval to find then it is OK
那么好了
because it wouldn't have helped me to go right anyway
我就知道就算向右搜索也帮不上什么了
because there is nothing in the right to be found.
因为在右边你也不会找到什么了
So it is not guaranteeing that
它不是保证
there is nothing to be found in the left,
左边什么都没有
but if there happens to be nothing to find in the left it is OK
只是说 如果左边什么都没找到
because there was nothing to be found in the right either.
你可以同时放弃右边了
That is what the second one says.
这就是第二点的内容
In either case, you're OK to go the way.
两个条件都很有用
So let's do this proof.
那我们来证明吧
Does everybody understand what the proof says?
大家都明白这个命题说的是什么了吧？
Understanding the proof is tricky. It's logic. Logic is tricky.
这个命题挺巧妙地 很有逻辑 逻辑就很巧妙
Suppose the search goes right. We'll do the first one.
假设搜索向右走了 那么我们先证明第一个命题
If left of x is NIL then we are done
如果x左结点是空的 那就完事了
since we proved what we wanted to prove.
因为命题就已经得证了
If we go right there are two possibilities,
如果我想右走 那么就有两种可能
either we have left of x be NIL or left of x is not NIL.
x的左结点是空的或者是非空的
So if it is NIL we are OK because we said
如果是空的 那就完事了 因为要证明的是
if it goes right I want to prove this,
如果往右搜索
that the things in the left subtree that overlap is empty.
左子树里面重叠区间的集合是空集
If there is nothing there,
如果右子树什么都没有
there is clearly nothing there that overlaps.
那左子树肯定也没有重叠的区间
Otherwise, the low of i is greater than m of the left of x.
否则的话 i的低端点比x的左子的m值大
If I look at x here, either x was NIL
看这里的x 在while判断语句里
in the while statement here or this is true.
要不然x是空值 要不然这条式就为真
We just said it is not NIL so let's take a look at,
我们已经说了它不为空 所以来看看这边
excuse me. I'm on the wrong line. I am in this loop.
抱歉 我看错行了 现在我在这个循环里
Left of x was not NIL and the low of i was this.
x的左结点不是空的 而且i的低端点是这个
Which way am I going here? I am going right.
这里我们向哪个方向走？向右走对吧
Therefore, this was not true.
因此这个命题是非真的
So either left of x was not NIL, which was the first one,
所以x的左结点可能不是空的 也就是第一个
or low of i is greater than m of left of x if I am going right.
或者i的低端点 比x的左子的m值还要大 那我就向右走
If I'm going right one of those two had to be true.
如果我向右边走 那么这两个里面肯定有一个是真的
The first one was easy.
第一条很简单
Otherwise, we have this, low of i is greater than m of left of x.
否则的话 我们可以得到这样的结果 i的低端点大于x左结点的m值
Now this has got to be that value.
现在它可能正好是某个值
m of left of x is the right endpoint,
x左结点的m值正好是一个右(高)端点
is the high endpoint of some interval in that subtree.
正好就是左子树某些区间的高端点
This is equal to the high of j for some j in L.
它等于L里一区间j的高端点
So m of left of x must be equal to the high of some endpoint
x左结点的m值就是某些区间的高端点
because that's how we're picking the m's.
因为m值就是这么选出来的
For some j in the left subtree.
从左子树的某个j区间选出来的
And no other interval in L has a larger high endpoint
在L中的其他区间的最高点  都没有比——
——than high of j. If I draw a picture here,
没有比j的高端点更大 如果用图来说明的话
I have over here i and this is the low of i.
这是i 然后这是i的低端点
And I have j where we say
对于区间j的话
its high endpoint is less than the low of i.
它的高端点要比i的低端点还要小
This is j, and I don't know how far over it goes.
这是j 我也不知道它有多长
And this has high of j
对于j的高端点来说
——which is the highest one in the left subtree.
他已经是左子树里面最大的了
There is nobody else who has got a higher right endpoint.
没有哪个高端点比它的还要高了
There is nobody else in this subtree
也就是说在这个子树里
who could possibly overlap I,
不可能有与i区间重叠的
because all of them end somewhere before this point.
因为那些区间都在这一点前面就结束了
This point is the highest one in a subtree.
这点已经是最大的高端点了
Therefore, i prime in L
因此 L中的i'区间
such that i prime overlaps i is the empty set.
i'区间与i区间重叠的部分就是空集
And now the hard case. Everybody stretch. Hard case.
现在到了难点了 没关系 我有姿势(知识)我自豪
Does everybody follow this?
还能跟得上吧？
The point is that because this is
问题的关键就是
the highest guy everybody else has to be left,
由于这已经是左子树里最高的了
so if you didn't overlap the highest guy
如果连最高的都没重叠
you're not going to overlap anybody.
那就谁都重叠不上了
Suppose the search goes left
假设要向左搜索
——and that there is nothing to overlap in the left subtree.
而且在左子树里没有发现重叠的区间
I went left here but I am not going to find anything.
我向左走也什么都没找到
Now I want to prove that it wouldn't have helped me to go right.
现在我要证明 在这种情况下往右走也是徒劳的
That's essentially what the theorem here says.
这是就是这个定理的主要内容
That if I assume this it wouldn't have helped to go right.
假设有这个条件 那向右走也没用
I want to show that there is nothing in the right subtree.
我要证明右子树里没有我们想要找的区间
So going left was OK
那到右子树也可以
because I wasn't going to find anything anyway.
除非你什么都不想找
Similarly, we go through a similar analysis.
其实差不多 分析的过程差不多
Low of i is less than or equal to m of the left of x,
i的低端点小于等于x左结点的m值
which once again is equal to the high of j for some j in L.
它还是等于L中某些区间j的高端点
We are just saying if I go left these things must be true.
就是说如果向左走的话 这些命题就都是真的
I went left. Since j is in L it doesn't overlap i,
如果往左走 既然j在L里而且与i不重叠
because the set of things that overlap i in L is empty set.
因为这个集合里与i重叠的区间是空集
Since j doesn't overlap i that implies that
既然j与i不重合
the high of i must be less than the low of j.
那么i的高端点一定小于j的低端点
Since j is in L and it doesn't overlap i,
既然L里面的j与i不重叠
what are the possibilities?
那么可能会怎样？
We essentially have here, if I draw a picture,
其实就是这样的 我来画个图说明
I have j and L and I have i here.
这是j 还有i
The point is that it doesn't overlap it,
注意他们并没重叠
therefore, it must be to the left
因此 它肯定是左边的
because its low endpoint is less than this.
因为它的低端点比这个还要小
But it doesn't overlap it,
但是他没重叠
therefore its high endpoint must be left of the low of this one.
因此它的高端点一定比这个低端点还要小
Now we will use the binary search tree property.
现在我们要用到二叉搜索树的性质了
That implies that for all i prime in R,
这就是说对于R中的所有i'区间
everything in the right subtree,
就是右子树里面的所有区间
we have a low of j is less than or equal to low of i prime,
我们可以得出j的低端点小于等于i'的低端点
so we're sorted on the low endpoints.
这次我们基本上是在讨论低端点
Everything in the right subtree must have a low endpoint
右子树里面的所有区间的低端点
that starts to the right of the low endpoint of j
都是位于j的低端点右面的
because j in the left subtree.
因为j是在左子树里
And everything in the whole tree is sorted by low endpoints,
整棵树里的所有区间都是按照低端点排序的
so anything in the right subtree is going to start over here.
所以右子树里的任何区间都是从这个地方开始的
Those are other things. These are the i primes in R.
这是另一棵子树里的 这些是R里的i'区间
We don't know how many there are,
我也不知道有多少
but they all start to the right of this point.
不过它们都是从这个点的右边开始的
So they cannot overlap i either,
所以它们也不会和i重叠
therefore, there is nothing.
因此 这里没有我们要找的东西
All the i primes in R is also nobody.
R里面的所有的i'都不重叠
Just to go back again, the basic idea is that
再来复习一下 大体的想法就是
since this guy doesn't overlap the guy who is in the left
既然它不和左子树的区间相交
and everybody to the right is going to be further to the right,
那么所有右子树的区间都要更加靠右
if I go left and don't find anything that's OK
所以当我在左边什么都没找到 那就完事了
because I am not going to find anything over here anyway.
因为在另一边我还是什么都找不到
They are not going to overlap.
右边也不会有重叠的
Data-structure augmentation, great stuff.
数据结构的扩张 很给力
It will give you a lot of rich, rich data structures
他会给你多姿多彩的数据结构
built on any ones you know,
可以从任何已知的数据结构出发
hash tables, heaps, binary search trees and so forth.
像哈希表 堆 二叉搜索树等等